[Music]
Stanford University we did not talk
about home hulks free energy did we we
did what did I say about home folks free
energy just a definition that it's the
logarithm that's related to the
logarithm of the partition that's all
okay great
oh we never got to the ideal gas at all
or my problem is I'm teaching this
course both in graduate school in here
and I'm completely for that we did we
proved the following identity we didn't
do that either okay let's assume that
for now
[Music]
or thought we had done the ideal gas
okay before we do the ideal gas I want
to get to the ideas of volume and arm
and free energy will need it so let's
let's define a concept I think I told
you last time that the logarithm of the
partition function or is there minus
sign I think there's a minus sign T
times the logarithm of the partition
function is called the Helmholtz free
energy a the hellmouth free energy has
an important meaning but before we get
into it or important usefulness before
we get into it did we did we count that
we proved all right you're going to have
to help me out did we prove the
relationship between energy free energy
and entropy we did or good so we don't
have to do that okay in particular
temperature times entropy minus the
energy is equal to the free energy okay
we did that good I'm armed or bollixed
up because of my confusions about the
one i'm teaching where okay so we don't
have to do that did we talk about
control parameters at all well we did
fluctuations but we did not do or
control it okay before we do the ideal
gas I would like to introduce the
concept of pressure and how you
calculate the pressure in a system this
is still more theory and less
application but still if we want to do
the ideal gas I think we bend or
pressure is okay the definition of
pressure is of course through the
definition of force on the walls we
could imagine if you like a cylinder
with a piston
and we could measure the force on this
piston due to the collisions of the
molecules with the piston and that would
define the pressure the pressure is the
force divided by the area of the pie up
by the area of the piston force divided
by area I only think I'll bother writing
that down we all know that so the
question is how do we calculate the
force on a system well we could try to
calculate the collision with the
molecules every time a molecule bounces
off it makes a sudden force on the
unhear an impulsive sudden force we can
average the force over enough time so
that the you know the actual force the
actual force is a very very Wiggly
function that jumps around a lot we
could average it over time and define a
pressure in that way that is not a
particularly convenient way to define
pressure nor is it a very general way
our molecules hitting walls are not the
only way that you can get pressure
another way for example you could get
pressure is there might be direct forces
not just collisional forces not just
some contact forces of the molecules
with the walls but there might be a
potential energy a long-range force of
some kind maybe not long-range but semi
long-range force between the molecules
and the piston and they might push a
pull on the piston and that would not
have to do with direct collisions so we
need a more general definition both of
force on force in general but in
particular force on the piston in this
particular setup now let me remind you
what the definition of forces and
mechanics the definition of force and
mechanics is that Rett is the change in
the potential energy of a system with
respect to position or the change of
potential energy with respect to some
co-ordinate let's write down the formula
just to remind you the change in the
potential energy let's write potential
energy let me call it u with respect to
a coordinate actually as minus the force
now that's a jest that we define the
pressure or the force on the cylinder
here on a piston as the change in energy
of the system with respect to motion of
the piston we can either think of the
change yeah that that's a good way to
think about it the change in the energy
of the system how much does it change
this is an energy of the system change
when we move the piston a little bit
another way to think about it is the
work done on the piston per unit
position change
alright the work done so if we can
calculate the change in energy now what
will that be that will be the change in
energy minus the change in energy of the
gas in here as we change the volume we
change the volume a little bit the
energy in there will change and that is
the work done on the piston it's also
minus the work done by the piston on the
gas energy conservation tells us that
the work done on the piston by the gas
is the same as the work done on the
minus sign the work done by the gas on
the piston so and we'll focus on the
work done by the piston on the gas so we
can imagine squeezing the gas a little
bit changing the volume or changing the
coordinate of the piston and the work
done on the gas or the change in energy
of the gas with respect to
small motion of the piston is of course
called the force on the piston is that
clear all right so that's that's a
definition the change in energy equal
Delta e divided by Delta X where X could
be the position of the of the piston X
that's the force on the piston it's
important in this context that we move
the piston slowly why let me give you a
crazy example supposing let's move the
piston outward ok the formula is still
true the change in energy of the gas
with respect to the location of the
piston is related to the force supposing
we jointly change the position of the
piston really fast so fast that we were
moving the piston faster than the
velocity of the molecules what would be
the force on the piston when it receded
very quickly away from the molecules
zero why because no molecule would bang
into the piston and so there would be no
force so it's important that we move the
piston slowly slowly so that some
average of the collisions can be can be
averaged over so we move the piston
slowly adiabatically is the word remove
the piston adiabatically and we
calculate the change in energy with
respect to position now if we multiply
this by the area of the piston I
shouldn't call it a because that's going
to be free energy let's call it little a
this becomes the force divided by little
a the area of the piston and what's
little a times Delta X that's the change
in volume all right the area of the
piston times the change in position of a
piston is the change in volume so we can
write that
are the change in energy divided by the
volume is the force divided by the area
what's the force divided by the area the
pressure now I have a feeling I have the
sign wrong and I'll tell you why it's
just it's a question of keeping clear in
your head whether we're talking about
the change in the energy of the gas or
the change in the energy of the position
of the of the piston when it's pushed
all right if I squeeze the gas do I
increase or decrease the energy of the
of the molecules inside you increase it
so just to check which switch the right
sign is I'm thinking of een au as the
energy of the gas not the energy of the
piston all right if I move the piston
inward I decrease the volume is that
correct all right but the pressure is
positive Delta e is positive Delta V is
negative so Delta e divided by Delta V
would be negative if I squeeze the gas a
little bit but that must correspond to
positive pressure so there must be a
minus sign here and there is so the
change in energy per unit volume is
minus the pressure and say that fun that
minus sign always seems a little
peculiar to me but it's right and as I
said that's the way to think about it
squeezing the gas decreases the volume
but increases the pressure okay that's
now again we must do it slowly otherwise
the point is that pressure is a concept
that is again an average concept
averaged over some time so you can't do
it instantly fast you better do it
slowly and what's more what's also
important is that in this formula that
the only changes in energy are due to
the motion of the piston I can imagine
other changes I could imagine that while
I that while I move the piston a little
bit slowly I could heat the gas but
putting a flame under it
okay let's see what all cool it will
take energy out of it
then this formula would not be right for
example I could squeeze the gas a little
bit which would tend to increase the
energy but at the same time remove heat
from the gas right well by connecting it
to a refrigerator I could decrease the
energy by removing heat but squeeze the
gas which would tend to increase the
energy the net effect being if I get if
I tuned it correctly to not change the
energy at all then I will have a change
in energy with response ER for the
pressure in fact it wouldn't necessarily
wouldn't necessarily need any pressure
to do that you just change the volume
remove heat you don't need any pressure
to do that in fact if you remove heat
the volume will naturally change by
itself
so it's important also that you not have
any other sources of energy coming into
and out of the system other than the
work done by moving the piston okay no
heat allowed in and out you move the
piston slowly what is such a process
called adiabatic
sure we'll do that what but we want to
first define pressure before we write
that there's a pressure term and another
term we've got to define pressure
okay now adiabatic also means at
constant entropy have we discussed that
or not I don't remember we haven't got
so let me explain to you why an
adiabatic process that means one done
slowly why that is a process at constant
entropy this is this really ultimately
comes from quantum mechanics so it can
be phrased in terms of classical
mechanics but it's easier to phrase it
in terms of it well we don't even need
quantum mechanics we don't need quantum
mechanics all we need is the idea that
there are energy levels and that the
energy levels are discrete now this is
the energy levels of a system but let's
see let's plot horizontally the volume
of the system so Haley R is a system
that has a collection of possible
energies the energies just being the
sums of the energies of all the
particles in there if we were doing
quantum mechanics the energies would be
discrete if we're not doing quantum
mechanics we then then we have to be a
little more careful but but in quantum
mechanics we have discrete energy levels
and we can label the I Fenner G level
horizontally we have the volume of the
system the energy levels are not
independent of a volume of the system if
you change the system by changing the
volume the energy levels will change for
example if you slowly change the volume
of the system then the values that I
don't mean the energy itself I mean the
values of the possible values of the
energy the energy levels of the system
the possible values of the energy they
will also change for example if you have
a box of a certain size if the size is
very small
the energy levels are very very well
separated this is a quantum mechanics
fact a small box it takes a lot of
energy to jump to the next level
the next energy level a large box it
only takes a small energy to jump to the
next energy level so as the volume
changes the energy levels themselves the
individual values of the energies of
both a single particle or just a whole
system they also change so let's imagine
plotting them as they change the energy
levels evolve typically as you make the
system bigger the energy levels decrease
so I've indicated them by a decreasing
function and so forth no not
particularly not no no reason for that
it's that it's on certain situations it
might be but in general are it's
typically again it doesn't have to be a
any particular kind of function of
volume but there is one there are two
important properties they are connected
to the issue of conservation of
information you can think of the
changing of the volume the slow changing
of the volume as a time evolution of a
system what do we know about the time
evolution of systems in both classical
mechanics and quantum mechanics number
one the levels no level disappears the
energy levels just evolved and they
don't disappear or reappear no new
energy levels appear as you change the
volume or any other control parameter a
control parameter means the thing that
you can dial slowly as you slowly dial a
control parameter I'll give you other
examples of control parameters but the
volume is the most familiar one the
energy levels don't disappear and number
two they don't cross each other
they don't cross and they don't
disappear they stay in the same order so
the lowest energy level stays lowest the
next one stays second lowest and so
forth that is a property of both quantum
mechanics and is an analogue of it in
classical mechanics now supposing we
start our system at a given energy level
and we slowly vary the control parameter
what happens there's a theorem about
this and the theorem is called the
adiabatic theorem it's a quantum
mechanics theorem there's an analogue of
it as I said for classical mechanics the
quantum mechanics theorem stet says that
the system as you change very slowly
change the control parameter the system
will remain in a state of definite
energy and it will just track along
these lines so if you start the system
over here with this precise value of the
energy and if you know the shape of
these curves you vary the volume slowly
you know that you wind up over here
again in a precise energy level what
happens if we know let's suppose our
state of knowledge in the initial state
is such that all we know is that we
start in one of these three levels one
of these three levels that's all we know
then after a period we know that we're
still in one of these three levels
that's all we know okay what happens if
we know that the probability for being
in one of these three levels is 1/2 1/4
and 1/4 1/2 1/4 well that does sum to 1
doesn't it yeah
1/2 1/4 and 1/4 what will the
probabilities for being in the different
levels of a here be 1/2 1/4 1/4 what
happens to the entropy if we start with
a given entropy here
it does not change why because the
probability distribution doesn't change
the probability of being in the eiffel
level doesn't change so we can say that
P of AI is an adiabatic invariant that's
the terminology an adiabatic invariant
means very slow change the probability
of being in the ice state even though
the energy of the ice state may change
the energy of each of these states
change how can that be consistent with
energy conservation because we do some
work by changing the parameters exactly
we do some work by changing the
parameters so the levels change meaning
to say the energy levels change the
energy that they have but the
probability of being in the IKE level
doesn't change and that assures that the
entropy which is after all just the
summation of P sub I log P sub body you
know what I mean P sub I but that
doesn't change so the entropy is an
adiabatic invariant let's come back now
this is this is really central that
energy is an ATI sorry entropy is an
eightieth energy is not an adiabatic
invariant entropy is an adiabatic
invariant and the ultimate reason for it
is information conservation without it
we could have energy levels running into
each other and all sorts of funny things
happening and the probability
distribution would not be an adiabatic
invariant okay let's come over to here
now we said that the pressure was the
rate of change of energy with respect to
volume with a minus sign in an adiabatic
process we now know that that means a
fixed entropy at fixed entropy so the
definition of pressure let's write it as
a calculus equation
- the pressure is the derivative of the
energy with respect to the volume
keeping fixed the entropy now keeping
fixed the int not keeping fix the
temperature certainly not keeping fixed
the energy the derivative of the energy
with respect to the energy is what 1
it's certainly not the derivative of
energy with respect to energy sorry I'm
sorry
here what I said the derivative of
energy with respect to volume have fixed
something defines the pressure that
something is the entropy okay think of
fixed entropy as first of all again
meaning do it slowly so that you have
time for things to average but also
without adding other forms of energy to
the system that you haven't accounted
for then that's not having to do with
this pressure then this is the
definition and that that is the
definition of pressure there's a more
general concept which I might as well
tell you there are other kinds of
control parameters besides volume let me
give you an example external magnetic
field again you can imagine a dial that
ramps up current or external electric
field which is a dial that Rance ramps
up the charge and capacitor plates or
anything like that those are also
control parameters and those control
parameters also when you change them do
work on a system same kind of formula
and you can write it more generally R
instead of volume we could introduce a
control parameter X volume replace it by
X whatever X is magnetic field or
anything else instead of pressure let's
define the variable Y that goes with X
the definition of Y is simply minus y is
equal to the derivative
energy with respect to X whatever X is a
constant entropy so there are lots of
things like this the most familiar and
will mostly work with this the most
familiar being volume and pressure these
variables come in pairs they come in
pairs Y which is the general force if
you like the derivative of energy with
respect to X and X they're called
conjugate thermodynamic variables the
most familiar again pressure and volume
the question is how do we calculate the
pressure well that's not so hard all we
have to do is figure out the energy as a
function of the entropy and the volume
and energy as a function of energy of
volume and entropy and then we can
differentiate keeping the entropy fixed
but calculating the entropy of a general
system is usually difficult it's usually
a pain in the neck frankly you can do it
but there's a simpler formula for the
pressure and the simple formula involves
not the rate of change of energy with
respect to volume at fixed entropy but
something else this is also equal to the
rate of change of something else with
respect to volume and fixed temperature
why is it easier to be able to deal with
fixed temperature the reason it's easier
to be able to deal with fixed
temperature is very simple when you
write the partition function everything
goes back to the partition function all
right you calculate the partition
function it's handed to you as a
function of temperature that's the
natural variable that's the variable
that the partition function is directly
presented to you as a function of and if
you can differentiate the appropriate
thing with respect to volume at fixed
temperature it's usually much easier
than first having to calculate the
entropy and then trying
differentiate something keeping the
entropy fixed usually much more
difficult this is easier what is the
thing that you differentiate the
Helmholtz free energy and the Helmholtz
free energy that's not so hard once you
know the partition function and its
logarithm you multiply it by the
temperature and then you differentiate
with really differentiate the Helmholtz
free energy with respect to the volume
all right now I haven't told you why
that's true
so since I don't like leaving loose ends
we should prove the theorem that says
let's see what it says it's a little
mathematics theorem not very hard well
it says that the derivative of energy
with respect to volume at fixed entropy
is the same as the derivative of the
free energy sorry this should be a my
yacht sinking no sorry it's the
derivative of the free energy with
respect to the volume at fixed
temperature I'd in order to prove this
we need a little bit of a theorem it's a
small theorem it's a calculus theorem
it's practically not a theorem it's just
a simple identity
let's see what the theorem is let's plot
to independence no questions alright so
let's plot horizontally the volume or it
could be any other control parameter the
theorem I'm going to teach you which is
in the notes you can apply to any
control parameter role but let's take
the volume as a special case and
vertically let's see what that I plot
vertically I think the temperature got a
temperature now let's imagine drawing
the lines let's see we need to line let
me see what lines we need what we need
now let's first start with a point now
this point at every point is a value of
energy and also of entropy the
temperature of you know the temperature
and you know the volume you know
everything about the system and you can
compute the energy and the entropy let's
see I want to make sure my diagram looks
consistent with one of my notes so yeah
alright we can also draw lines of
constant entropy and energy what do they
look like I don't know what they look
like but let's draw in just some
arbitrary lines here's a line of
constant energy and let's put in a line
of constant entropy right through that
point so the entropy along this line is
constant and the energy along this line
is constant s equals constant s equals
constant energy equals constant
now what do I want to compute I want to
compute the rate of change of energy
with respect to volume and fixed entropy
that's the pressure that is the pressure
minus the pressure all right but I would
like to compute it in terms of
derivatives with respect to temperature
when we compute it in a different way
all right so what are we computing here
let's take a differential change in
volume is a differential change in
volume DV this is the change in energy
when I change the volume a little bit
keeping the entropy fixed so it's the
difference between the entropy at the
energy at this point and this point is
that clear that's not clear we might as
well not go any further the rate of
change of energy when we change the
volume a little bit is the difference
between the energy here and the energy
here divided by DV of course divided by
DV here's how I'm going to calculate it
I'm going to calculate the change in the
energy when I go horizontally that's at
fixed temperature and then when I drop
down vertically so the change in energy
and going from here to here is the sum
of two terms the first is the change in
energy at fixed temperature
this is the change this should be
partial derivative partial derivative of
energy with respect to volume at fixed
temperature that's this change here and
then there's the vertical change okay
what is the vertical change well and
going from here to here the entropy
changes why does the entropy change
because the entropy is different over
here than it is over here the entropy
was constant along here it has a
different value or music different color
the entropy has a different value over
here and so we can compute the change in
the energy going from here to here as
the change give me energy
with respect to the entropy we're
changing the entropy a little bit times
the change in the entropy when we go
from here to here the change in the
energy with respect to the entropy times
the change in the entropy will give us
the change in the entropy all right so
we have to multiply this by the change
in the entropy when we change what when
we go from this curve to this curve it
doesn't matter whether we go from this
curve to this curve from here to here or
from here to here why because the
entropy is constant along these lines so
the change in the entropy the energy is
the change in the energy per unit volume
at fixed temperature that's the
horizontal change plus the vertical
change which is the change in the energy
with respect to the entropy time
a change in the entropy in dropping down
vertically what's the change in the
entropy and dropping down vertically
it's the change in the entropy dropping
down vertically change in the entropy
with respect to the temperature at fixed
volume fixed volume is vertical what's
that the s PI V yeah we're not changing
the volume going down yeah it's the same
whether we go down and we go left I
happen what's the question you could use
either one we can use either one okay
okay
no okay good good good what is this this
is de by D s at fixed something the e by
D s have fixed X sorry a fixed volume
yeah at fixed volume okay the e da by D
s at fixed volume times the s by DT at
fixed now I've got something wrong here
the s by DX at fixed temperature the s
the s pie-ya the e by the SFX vol the s
by the volume - sorry the s by E by the
D heavy the e the e by the acid fixed
volume times the change in s in going
from here to here the change in s from
going to here to here is the s by the
volume at fixed act at fixed T I have
too many variables in my formulas
alright the change in going from here to
here in the entropy is the turret change
in entropy with respect to volume as
fixed temperature that's the formula
that we want I think yeah that's the
formula that we want okay now yeah I
will alright we have this which is de by
D volume the fixed temperature okay Oh
better yet let's just write de let's not
even write the e DV the change in energy
and going from here to here is the
derivative of energy with respect to
volume at fixed temperature times the
change in volume and going from here to
here right that's one term that's in
going from here to here
and then vertically going downward is
minus the derivative of energy
with respect to a change in the entropy
the entropy here and the entropy here is
different at fixed volume that's because
I've dropped vertically times the change
in the entropy in going from here to
here and that's it in this formula you
can think of volume and entropy is the
independent variables change in energy
with a sort of temperature volume
derivative with respect to energy
keeping the derivative of energy with
respect to volume keeping temperature
fixed
that's horizontal the derivative of
energy with respect to entropy at fixed
volume times the change in entropy and
going from here to here in this formula
you can think of the energy as a
function of volume and entropy
yeah-yeah-yeah-yeah
but whatever it is it's the change in
energy with respect to volume keeping
the temperature fixed that's the
coefficient that goes with volume and
the other one is derivative with respect
to entropy times the change in entropy
ah why because you're going from here
back to here rather than showing here to
here you're going from here down to here
and so this is the sign is negative sign
is negative if you just spend some time
with it you'll see why the time is there
why it's negative okay now what is the
change in entropy and going from here to
here that's this over here the change in
entropy and going from here to here is
also the change in entropy from going
from here to here
you know you're right it really is
positive are the change in entropy and
going from here to here is the same as
the change in entropy and going from
here to here but that's - the change in
entropy of going from here to here
that's where the minus sign comes from
and going from here to here so it's the
change in entropy and going from here to
here and that involves a minus sign this
DS is the change in entropy and going
from this point to that point which is
minus the change in entropy of going
from that point to that point ok what's
the change in entropy of going from here
to here it's the derivative of the
entropy with respect to the volume at
fixed temperature that's the change in
entropy going from here to here at fixed
temperature yeah
times DV
now it's not equal to zero it's a change
in energy and going from here here
that's what it is now if I divide it by
the volume then I get the derivative of
energy with respect to volume along this
line which is constant entropy that's
equal derivative of energy with respect
to volume at fixed temperature DV minus
the derivative of energy with respect to
entropy at fixed volume say it again
yeah yeah figured the vo I have a
certain threshold when the symbols just
get too many
I just really lose them the edv of fixed
temperature minus the e the S at fixed
volume the s by DV at fixed temperature
that's my first line yeah I just rewrote
it okay now why is it interesting this
is the thing Oh incidentally this is a
calculus theorem here I haven't done it
I haven't used the interpretation of
these variables yet this is a calculus
theorem about relationships between
derivatives with respect to two
different variables so it's a it's not a
it's not a deep theory the theorem about
energy and entropy or anything else it's
just a fan of the calculus theorem okay
now now let's apply it to the real thing
what is the derivative of the energy
with respect to the entropy at fixed
volume now a fixed volume we're talking
about a system with no change in the
control parameter it's just the same
kind of system we studied before we even
talked about control parameters you
remember before we introduced control
parameters to do work on the system
you remember what the e by D s was
temperature so now we use some physics
now we're going beyond calculus and we
can write that the e by DV I've fixed s
which is the pressure which is minus the
pressure that's the thing we're trying
to calculate that's equal to de by the V
at fixed temperature well it's a lot
easier to calculate things at fixed
temperature than it is a fixed energy so
that's a good sign all right I just
rewrote this over here and then - but
this is just the temperature the e by
the acid fixed volume temperature times
the s by DV at fixed temperature all I'm
doing is using a little bit of physics
the physics wasn't saying that the e by
D s at fixed volume was temperature and
a little bit of calculus to write down
this theorem and I have succeeded in
writing the pressure in terms of
derivatives with respect to temperature
instead of with rosario derivatives at
fixed temperature instead of at fixed
entropy that is an advantage because it
means you don't have to go and calculate
the entropy and keep it constant while
you're varying the volume all right but
this is even simpler this over here is
the same as the derivative of TS with
respect to the volume at fixed T why is
that because the derivative of F of T
with respect to P yeah yeah
okay so I can pull the T inside the
derivative and this is just the
derivative of TS with respect to volume
at fixed temperature and this is the
derivative of energy with respect to
volume at fixed temperature the result
is that this is equal to the derivative
with respect to the volume at fixed
temperature of e minus TS e minus TS and
that's them and that's minus the
pressure okay these two terms combine
together to just say derivative which
they're both derivatives with respect
the volume at fixed temperature and the
result is derivative of e minus TS a
fixed volume well what is e minus TS
it's a the Helmholtz free energy the
Helmholtz free energy so we now have a
lovely theorem that says that pressure
is equal to let's rewrite it pressure is
equal to minus not the derivative of the
ordinary energy but the derivative of
the Helmholtz free energy hmm this is
the Helmholtz it is minus the derivative
it should be minus the river the
Helmholtz free energy with respect to
the volume at fixed e I think I've got
it right yeah okay and that's an
enormous simplification because the
Helmholtz free energy is just simply
related to the logarithm of the
partition function you don't even have
to differentiate it to get the energy
you have to differentiate the partition
function and to keep the entropy fixed
you have to calculate the entropy so you
have to do two procedures one of which
can be rather complicated you have to if
you wanted to use energy and entropy you
have to differentiate to get the end
and then you would have to keep the
entropy fixed and believe me that's a
nuisance the other hand the whole
theorem simply tells you to calculate
the pressure all you have to do is
differentiate the logarithm of the
partition function at fixed temperature
with respect to the volume so if you can
calculate the partition function as a
function of temperature and volume your
home you have the pressure so that's
what we're going to do we're going to do
that now for the free gas so we take our
five-minute break this is a fundamental
equation there's a more general version
of it there's a more general version of
it
where things like pressure are
derivatives of the Helmholtz free energy
with respect to other control parameters
but these are this is the basic one
we're going to use at least for today
what we're going to calculate is the
pressure energy and all the various
properties of the ideal gas we now know
enough to do that and we can apply it to
a simple statistical mechanical system
we'll take five minutes and all right we
want to apply our tools now we have a
lot of tools partition function free
energy real energy entropy we have all
these tools theorems of various kinds
we'd like to apply it to a simple system
the simplest interesting system are well
an interesting simple system is the
ideal gas the ideal gas is a system of
point particles which are non
interacting are no structure to the
particles we can modify that later we
can allow them to have some internal
structure but without any internal
structure point particles filling a
volume v
the object is to calculate all the
thermodynamic properties of it by
computing the partition function and
then applying the various tools that we
have all right now we have to in order
to do the partition function we have to
sum over States
there's our sum over states of a system
here's our system the states of a
classical mechanical system are not
discrete things like that they're
continuous they characterized by
positions and momenta that means that
the sum over States is going to be
replaced by an integral I'm not going to
spend a lot of time explaining that
procedure but what are we going to be
integrating over all of the things that
characterize the state of the system so
if the system has n particles capital n
particles then its state is described by
3n coordinates namely the 3n positions
of the molecules and the 3n components
of momenta that means that the sum of
the states will be replaced by an
integral integrals and sums are costs
the same thing in some limit in quantum
mechanics it would literally be the sum
in classical mechanics we have to bend
our definitions a little bit to include
the possibility of continuous sums and
to characterize the state of the system
momentum and position alright so what do
I replace the sum by an integral over
the position of every particle that
means the three n X 3 n X integrations
for each particle sorry 3 integration
for each particle the three coordinates
of space x y&z and the three components
of momentum I'll just indicate it that
way
those are that replaces the sum now what
do i sum normally i sum e to the minus
beta times the energy of the ithe level
instead we're going to have e to the
minus the energy but not the energy of
the ice level but the energy of a state
with particles at position X and
momentum P so what are we right here we
write the energy is the sum over all the
particles in the system there's a
contribution to the energy from every
particle let's write its sum of a little
n to indicate the particles and what's
the energy if there are no forces
between the particles and let's also
assume that there's no gravitational
field or anything like that it's just
particles in a box then the only energy
is the kinetic energy of the particles
so it's the sum of n of P sub n that
means the end particle squared divided
by twice the mass and that's it let me
write that the or on one line not two to
the M but momentum of the nth particle
squared and that of course means px
square plus py squared plus PZ squared
so this is the sum over all the squared
momenta all three n of them divided by
twice the mass and I'm assuming all of
the particles have the same mass now
that's it almost there's one other thing
that needs to be taken into account
that's the following idea here's an odd
we're going to assume that all of the
particles are identical you can't tell
them apart so let's imagine we have a
state I'm going to draw the particles as
little disks that really point particles
but you won't be able to see them if I
draw them as points
little disks the particles now supposing
I interchange these two particles is
that the same state or is it a different
state well now as a matter of
interpretation and not to interpretation
exactly in fact it actually doesn't
matter in the end
but it's but if they're really identical
particles and there's no difference
between them then interchanging two of
them is the same state as before okay
so supposing there's only two particles
and I integrate over all possible states
I'm double counting I'm double counting
because I'm counting each configuration
twice if I call this the first particle
in the second particle this is the same
configuration this is not a Q this is
just a particle this is the same as
particle two over here in particle 1
over here so that means I would have to
divide by two what if there are three
particles what do I divide by if there
are n particles n factorial right so to
keep track of the fact that the
particles are all physically identical
that an interchange of two of them is a
trivial non change of the state we put a
1 over n factorial in front of it all
right this is what we want to calculate
that's the partition function and as e
of beta but it's also a function of the
volume where does the volume come into
this well the X integrations are done
over some range and the range of the X
integrations is the interior of the box
of gas right so implicitly
there's also a dependence in fact I mean
in principle there could be a dependence
not just on the volume but the shape of
the box
however in this particular case it's
really only the volume that comes in the
temperature and the volume now the
integrand here does not depend on X at
all so that means I can do the X
integrations immediately and what does
it what though what does each X
integration supposing I focus on a
particular particle let's say the first
particle DX 1 this is d 3 X 1 what is
that integral it's just the volume I
have in such integrals and so I get a
factor which is volume to the enth
volume to the n divided by n factorial
incidentally volume to the nth over N
factorial can be re-expressed in a neat
way I'll write it out here for you but
for the moment I'm going to leave it in
the form that it is but let me just
reexpress it for you volume to the end
without the N factorial you couldn't do
this volume to the enth of n factorial
now what Sterling's approximation to n
factorial for large n n to the N not the
law n to the N e to the minus n right
the other way know which is equal to e
to the N V to the N over N to the N
which in turn e
e to the N that's just oh it's there but
there it's e times the volume over N to
the N now what is V over N or n over V
density n over V is the density so in
fact this is e divided by the density
Rho to the power n in other words for
each particle in the system there is a
factor of 1 over density in the
partition function will use that another
time I'm not going to use that today but
it's interesting to notice that this
thing combines itself in together
such a way is to give a factor of 1 over
the density for each particle alright
that's a useful fact that will come up
another time but for the time being
let's just leave it this way the reason
I want to leave it in terms of the
volume because later on I want to
differentiate with respect to the volume
to calculate the pressure okay here is
the entire dependence on the volume
there is no other dependence on the
volume and the rest of it is just this P
integration so we have to figure out how
to do the P integration and the P
integration is actually easy there are
three n identical integrals in other
words it's the 3n power of a basic
integral the basic integral is a one
dimensional integral e to the minus P
squared now P squared does not mean px
square plus py square plus PZ squared it
just means a one-dimensional variable e
to the minus P squared beta over 2m just
this integrated DP alright I don't
remember if we discussed to do did we
discuss Gaussian integrals we did not
not this quarter let's discuss Gaussian
integrals quickly we'll do it quickly
this integral let's not call it P let's
just call it L e to or Y e to the minus
y squared dy
where to where from minus infinity to
infinity these momentum integrations go
from minus infinity to infinity can
momentum be negative yes it just means
going in the negative direction this
integral is just a number it's a
convergent integral and it's just a
number okay anybody know what the number
is
it's just square root of pi period
square root of pi square root of pi how
the hell do you get a square root of pi
in a formula
well since the answer square root of pi
if you want to if you want to do the
integral it's smart to do the square of
the integral the square of the integral
will be pi I'm not kidding that's right
that's the way you do the integral you
square it and then you can do the
integral you can't do the integral the
way it is you can do it if you square it
alright some other time I will do the
integral for you but not today okay so
to do this integral here it's sort of of
this form but there's an extra
coefficient in front of the Y squared
namely beta over 2m all I have to do is
change variables let me change variables
so that P squared times beta over 2m is
y squared
that just means you've changed variables
that P is equal to the square root of 2m
over beta times y that's all then P
squared will be 2m over beta times y
squared and what's in the exponent here
will just be simple it will be what e to
the minus y squared but what happens to
DP the P is not the Y but rather the Y
times to M let me put it on the outside
2m over beta to the power 1/2
and now I've done the integral the
integral is the square root of pi as
this times this factor here oh yeah
why then away
where
where is your wife
is this right yeah I replaced the P by D
Y times the square root of 2m over beta
which is the same as two M over beta to
the one-half power and then the integral
is just the square root of pi and so
this altogether is to M PI over beta to
the one half power
that's that we've done in the basic
integral how many such powers how many
powers of that integral are there three
in one for each component of the
momentum so the whole partition function
has now been done it is 2m pi divided by
beta to the power n twice n divided by
three no just it's a three-hit divided
by 2/3 n divided by 2 I can't think
without my pants notice the whole the
whole thing is something apart yeah even
the N factorial is approximately the nth
power of something simple if we were to
have plugged back in the density and all
that stuff this is just the nth power of
something in other words there's a
factor for each particle the fact we
could have done it for one particle and
then just taken the nth power of it and
that would pretty much give us the right
answer okay so this is the partition
function Z it depends on the volume and
for fixed volume
it depends only on the temperature
volume is a control factor and and beta
is the temperature now
first of all let's calculate the energy
per particle Oh before we do that let's
take the logarithm of it
I want logarithm of Z
the logarithm of Z is equal to well as -
logarithm of n factorial over here then
is plus log n log V and log of the
volume that's from here and then there
is minus 3n over 2 log beta that comes
from here it's minus because the beta
was in the denominator
and then there's plus 3n over 2 log of
what 2m pi that's it
we could write this argue I leave it as
an assignment to you to rewrite this in
terms of the density instead of the
volume and in you'll find that it's
basically n times logarithm of the
density the N factorial and the V
combined together to give you logarithm
of the density but I'm not going to do
that now okay
that's it that's log of the partition
function let's first calculate the
energy per particle all right
let's calculate the energy before the
energy per particle notice that only
interesting terms well we'll see what's
interesting in a minute let's calculate
the energy per particle what's the
formula for the energy general formula
doesn't depend on the fact that it's a
free gas just very general formula minus
the derivative of log of Z with respect
to beta energy is equal to minus the
derivative of log Z with respect to beta
well it's all laid out for us that's
equal the plus 3n the minus is here and
here cancel and we get plus 3n over 2
and the derivative of log beta with
respect to beta is just 1 over beta
what's 1 over beta temperature so the
total energy of the gas is three halfs T
times the number of particles and the
energy per particle energy per particle
is just three halfs the temperature if I
put the change units and use the
standard textbook unit convention I
would replace capital T by kt by
Boltzmann's constant times let's say
Boltzmann constant times little T three
halfs Katie I won't do that I'm not
going to follow that convention but I
just wanted to point out three halves KT
is the textbook answer where did that
first of all where did the 1/2 come from
in the formula the 1/2 came from the
square roots in the Gaussian integral
right it came from the square roots in
the Gaussian integral it came from the
for the Gaussian integral where the 3
come from the three dimensions of space
so basically there's a kinetic energy
per Direction per particle which is 1/2
T per direction per particle the three
directions of space if there was 26
dimensions of space then it would be 26
over 2 I pick 26 at random it had
nothing to do with string theory right
just 20 huh
yeah $28 26 is the letters of the
alphabet
okay so e over N is 3 halves the
temperature or three halves KT if you
like if you wanted to plug in numbers
and use 300 degrees at room temperature
you'd want to plug in their Boltzmann
constant which is 10 to the minus 23 or
something and you would find the energy
per particle is 10 to the minus what 21
or something like that in joules so it's
pretty small okay so that's the first
step or the first little thing we can
calculate next let's calculate the
pressure that's an interesting to
caffeine to calculate to calculate the
pressure we first calculate the we want
to calculate the derivative of the
energy with respect to volume have fixed
entropy but that's too hard so let's
calculate the derivative of the free
energy with respect to the with respect
to the volume at fixed temperature
that's a lot easier okay so let's do
that first we need the free energy a
a is equal to minus T log Z and we
wanted and we want to differentiate a
with respect to volume - it is pressure
okay the only term which is going to
contribute only the terms which depend
on the volume are going to contribute to
this derivative we might as well throw
away everything else nothing else will
give us a derivative with respect to
volume remember we're doing this at
fixed temperature this is a fixed
temperature so a fixed temperature this
is just a constant when I'm
differentiating this is a constant the
only thing which depends on the volume
at fixed temperature is this volume term
that's it that's how easy it is okay
let's see what we get the derivative of
T this is minus T times the derivative
of log V with respect to V now do I have
a ya n log V and that's just so Roma
writing I want to write the derivative
of the free energy that should be an
next line here on the next line this is
equal to n over V period I think that's
it
no times T times T the T over here no
minus sign because there are two minus
sign down okay can everybody see this
minus sign over here there's a minus
sign right where my finger is
- the adv is P but a is minus T log Z so
the two minus signs go away and when I
differentiate I just get in over V times
the factor T they'll have the ideal gas
law the ideal gas law P is PV equals n T
pressure times volume is the number of
particles times the temperature that's
the standard ideal gas law of course in
textbook notation this would be PV
equals n KT and then we can write that
if we like as pressure width divided by
volume if we like and we can write that
n over V is the density of particles Rho
Rho K T so it tells us that pressure is
proportional to density times
temperature okay forget the k and my
units in which temperature has units of
energy it's pressure is equal to density
times temperature that's the ideal gas
law
that's a particle density not the not
the mass density but a particle density
right
so and as you see we don't need any we
don't need to think about the molecules
we don't have to think about the
collisions with the walls we don't have
to we just mechanically we mechanically
carry out the statistical mechanical
definition of pressure the statistical
mechanical definition of energy all in
terms of the most fundamental variable
which is the partition function yeah
good question how did we get rid of a
mass the mass where was the mass in the
partition function that's over here
differentiating it it's just a constant
yeah isn't that remarkable that the
pressure doesn't depend on the mass it
is remarkable neither does the average
kinetic energy the average average
kinetic energy has gotten by
differentiating with respect to beta so
if you put a bowling ball in a gas the
kinetic energy of the bowling ball will
be exactly the same as the kinetic
energy of the of a single molecule of
anything or if you make the bowling ball
will have the same kinetic energy as the
energy of any other molecule it will
have a much smaller velocity so yeah so
that's so that's a good point that the
energy that the mass cancels out of
these formulas oddly what else what else
is interesting about this formula
oh right the H bar is just a convention
it's a convention I'll tell you what the
convention why there's a convention the
original definition of the partition
function is a sum was a dimensionless
was a dimensionless let's let's talk
about that little bit was a
dimensionless quantity in the exponent
the thing in the exponent was
dimensionless e to the minus beta beta
has units of 1 over energy times energy
this is dimensionless and it's just a
sum so the usual definition of the
partition function are the partition
function is dimensionless on the other
hand with this definition here the
partition function has the dimensions of
whatever x times momentum to the 3n
power are now x times momentum is not
dimensionless it has units of what is
called action ah it is not dimensionless
to make it dimensionless what we do is
and it won't change any answer as I'll
show you why in a minute but to make it
dimensionless what we just do is divide
each factor of an x times a P by a
physical quantity by a by a constant of
nature with the dimensions of X times P
it doesn't matter what console it
doesn't matter what we divide it by in
fact but just to give it the right
dimensions we divide by plunks constant
every time we see an x by x p we divide
by Planck's constant and that gives us
some factors of Planck's constant what
will it do in the partition function
here it will give us another minus in
[Music]
logarithm of Planck's constant ok
doesn't make any difference to anything
because we're always differentiating a
partition function makes no difference
to anything are differentiating the
partition function to calculate
various quantities or differentiating a
logarithm of the partition function this
just doesn't contribute so it's a
convention that's right it's only two
terms in this expression here which are
being differentiated right say it again
no I think it's in oh no there's a three
and yes thank you it's 3 n 3 n okay in
fact it's kind of interesting if we
really did do quantum mechanics or we
did the quantum mechanics of the free
gas a free ideal gas this term would
actually appear there naturally just by
summing over States we would discover it
yeah so this is a quick and dirty and
shorthand way of calculating the effects
of quantum mechanics does it come in to
anything not really nothing is nothing
interesting so at least not until we
start exploring quantum mechanics then
it does have an interesting consequence
but the interesting point about it what
does it do to the entropy incidentally
it does contribute to the entropy if we
go back to the connection between
remember there's a connection between
beta times the energy the free energy
wow it would add a constant to the
entropy but again adding constants to
the entropy doesn't change anything ok
um that is the ideal gas the ideal gas
law it is interesting to calculate the
entropy how would we calculate the
entropy it's interesting to calculate it
if for no other reason than to see that
it's fairly complicated and that you
would not want to try to calculate
derivatives of anything keeping the
entropy fixed let's just look at the
entropy let's see there's a formula for
the entropy in terms of I think it's a
minus e and then there must be a beta I
think that's right huh all right so
let's let's calculate that and see what
kind of nasty acara thing we get first
of all a is armed 1 over beta log Z
that's easy if I know the partition
function in other words beta times ei
just gives me log Z - now what's e in
terms of log Z the derivative of log Z
all I think times beta right is it E - a
or a - E you - a I can never remember
okay
alright so it's a sum of two terms the
the sum of the two terms s as is first
of all equal to minus log Z that's not
the hard to calculate plus beta or - I
guess no - a plus plus beta D log Z by D
beta okay that's not so bad that the but
if we actually go and calculate it we're
going to find out that it's kind of a
mess I'm not too bad a mess but just for
the free gas alone for the free gas
alone it has it has logarithms in it and
the logarithms are sort of hateful it
has things which are logarithms and
things which are not logarithms so let's
see what it has it has logarithms of Z
which is all this stuff in particular
the important pieces of it are n log V
minus 3n over 2 log beta Plus this
constant stuff over here which is not
important when we differentiate it and
then and then beta D log Z by D beta but
this is just the energy the log Z by D
beta was minus the energy so this is
minus beta I think it's minus beta times
the energy and what was the energy the
energy was three-halves n times t over
beta sorry
yeah the betas cancel I think the betas
cancel I think the betas cancel the
why did the beta's cancel yeah the
beta's cancel so this is the entropy and
the entropy involves logarithm of
logarithm of beta and so if I try to
calculate well it's just a little bit
complicated in this particular case if I
try to calculate the the pressure as a
derivative of the energy with respect to
volume keeping entropy fixed I would
have to remember to keep log beta fixed
that's a little bit of a nuisance it's
more complicated than just
differentiating the free energy with
respect to the volume keeping beta fixed
keeping the energy fixed sorry keep
differentiating the energy keeping the
entropy fixed is a more complicated
process and where you have to remember
to keep this fixed as you differentiate
the energy with respect to the volume
this is the tip of the iceberg because
this is an extremely simple system the
free gas normally the entropy is a
rather complicated and nasty function
and keeping it fixed while you
differentiate the energy can be very
hard on the other hand if you can
calculate the partition function all you
have to do is differentiate the volume
keeping the free energy keeping log Z
fixed and that's that's your that's
that's the fewer steps so Helmholtz free
energy is a good thing and as all sorts
of applications and its main advantage
is that the things that you calculate
are generally at fixed temperature any
questions yeah
I don't know I really don't know I think
I suspect it has to do with well there
was a thing in mathematics called the
partition function which is the number
of ways of summing up I don't know the
origin of it but it probably has to do
with partitioning the energy into these
bins there how many ways are they were
partitioning the energy but I don't know
for sure don't know again I don't know
this terminology is historical and I do
not know what's free about it I don't
know nothing I don't know and it's not
the only kind of free energy it's the
Helmholtz free energy what does it have
to do with Helmholtz again they don't
know there's also a Gibbs free energy
question the free energy help humble
tree energy sit stickers in their design
fly it's an equilibrium it only pertains
to an equilibrium state well the whole
idea of a partition function now again
it's one of these things if there are
very slow variations you can ascribe a
free energy to small volumes as long as
things are varying slowly over distance
in time so another example or another
general way in which free energy is
important if you have a well let's first
take the
supposing you have a moveable partition
this is just an example a moveable
partition with gas on both sides and the
partition is a is free to transmit
energy between the two parts of the
system then it will have pressure on it
from both sides what is the equilibrium
configuration the equilibrium
configuration of this partition is when
the pressure from both sides are equal
in other words when the net force on the
partition is equal to zero all right
that means that the derivative of the
free energy of the left side with
respect to the volume of the left side
must equal the derivative of the free
energy of the right side with respect to
the volume of the right side but a small
change in the volume of the left side
will give you the negative of the small
change of the volume on the right side
so if we refer everything let's say to
the left side this would become minus
the derivative of the right sided free
energy with respect to the volume of the
left side in other words we will write
that the derivative of the free energy
left plus right just transpose to the
other side left plus right with respect
to the position of the partition is
equal to zero okay we would just put
this on the other side and then the free
energy on the left plus the free energy
free energies add free energy on the
Left plus the free energy on the right
is minimized okay now
that's at constant temperature remember
these things are derivatives at constant
temperature so the meaning of this is
the following that if the whole system
is in a heat bath if the whole system is
in a heat bath which keeps it at
constant temperature as the changes
happen the heat bath is enormous so as
changes happen assume the temperature of
the heat bath doesn't change if the
system is in a gigantic heat bath and we
want to find out the equilibrium
position of this partition its where the
free energy is stationary not where the
original ordinary energy is stationary
so equilibrium in a situation where the
temperature is held constant temperature
typically is held constant by being in a
big heat bath if the temperature is
being held constant then the mechanical
equilibrium happens not where the energy
is minimum but where the free energy is
minimum that's a bit of a surprise you
might have expected where it's where the
energy is minimum it is not that's where
the free energy is minimum now of course
in saying that you're in a heat bath
it's assumed that energy can flow back
and forth into the system here so that's
it that's a big advantage of free energy
that it establishes where equilibrium is
in the system kept the fixed temperature
is something - made when you were
driving the pressure
[Music]
loudly no what we derived under those
circumstances under the adiabatic
circumstances is that you do use the
ordinary energy we've swapped ordinary
energy for free energy and adiabatic for
isothermal adiabatic is harder as a
general rule an isothermal isothermal
means a fixed temperature so right you
you would get a different okay so you
would get a different actually you get a
different equilibrium position if you
had adiabatic walls which didn't allow
energy into and out of the system then
the temperature would not be kept
constant and the partition model would
move the pertinent you do with partition
function the partition here would move
in a way which would minimize the energy
but if you're keeping in a constant
temperature with energy flowing into an
out of the system then the equilibrium
is when the free energy is has minimized
so that's an important distinction and
sometimes it's really important for some
problems because a free end you get a
different answer you get the wrong
answer if you minimize the energy any
other questions
okay.what mostly what I want I want to
impress are many of you there are many
things first of all the ideal gas is a
interesting system by itself but the
main thing I wanted to impress on you is
the power of knowing the partition
function the power of knowing the
partition function are once the
partition function is calculated a
series of almost mechanical steps will
derive for you energy pressure entropy
fluctuations we haven't talked about
fluctuations and pressure but that's an
interesting thing in itself as the
pressure fluctuate and just about every
thermodynamic relationship every
thermodynamic quantity can can be
computed from the partition function by
a relatively simple thing of usually
differentiating the partition function
so it's a powerful tool okay for more
please visit us at stanford.edu